<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mens sana in corpore sano a discourse upon recovery from sickness : directing how natural health may be improved into spiritual, especially by them that have lately recovered it.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50141</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11795672</idno>
  <idno type="VID">49307</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240879016</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31240</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11795672</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49307)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1487:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mens sana in corpore sano a discourse upon recovery from sickness : directing how natural health may be improved into spiritual, especially by them that have lately recovered it.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Green and J. Allen for Samuel Phillips ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston in N.E. [i.e. New England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cotton Mather by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages faded, stained and torn, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: folio A2 torn, all after p. 46 wanting.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sin.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Man (Christian theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49307:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49307:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Mens Sana in Corpore Sano.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Discourse UPON RECOVERY FROM Sickness.</p>
            <p>Directing How <hi rend="italic">Natural</hi>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Health,</hi> may be Improved into <hi rend="italic">Spiritual:</hi> Especially by them that have lately <hi rend="italic">Recovered</hi> it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Isa. XXXVIII. 9.</bibl>
               <p rend="italic">The Writing,—When he had been Sick, and was Recovered of his Sickness.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Haec Tibi, Si Recipis, dat Pagina Grata Salutem;</l>
               <l>Si Renuas, Eadem Pagina Testis erit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">BOSTON</hi> in <hi rend="italic">N. E.</hi> Printed by <hi rend="italic">B. Green,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">J. Allen,</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Samuel Phillips,</hi> at the Brick Shop. 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:49307:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49307:2"/>
            <head>Preface.</head>
            <p>THE Discourses, Written by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of the Gospel, on their own <hi rend="italic">Recovery from Sickness,</hi> have often been grateful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments unto the Churches of God, in many <hi rend="italic">other Lands,</hi> as well as in both <hi rend="italic">Englands:</hi> This Page cannot hold the <hi rend="italic">Catalogue,</hi> that I could give of such Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses. Nevertheless, The Author of the Ensuing, had not permitted<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on thereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, if there be<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi rend="italic">Recovery from Sickness,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of it: for what can t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerned in the Good<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of so <hi rend="italic">Mean</hi> a Person?<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Sermon Preached, whe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> yea, Thousands of the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly had their <hi rend="italic">Health</hi> Re<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi rend="italic">Epidemical Calamity:</hi> And<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:49307:3"/>
               <hi rend="italic">Author,</hi> but some of <hi rend="italic">Them,</hi> that have now Committed unto the Press, this <hi rend="italic">Feeble Essay</hi> of one Scarce got free from the <hi rend="italic">Illness,</hi> which had for near a Month been Breaking him; and one so willing, to be conceal'd from the Notice of Mankind, that he can gladly say, <hi rend="italic">Modo haec Lectori Sint usui, Quemvis Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorem Fingito:</hi> May the <hi rend="italic">Reader</hi> be Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, its no matter who's the <hi rend="italic">Author!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, <hi rend="italic">Reader,</hi> Whether thou art <hi rend="italic">Sick,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Well;</hi> I address thee, as the <hi rend="italic">Jews</hi> did use to Salute their <hi rend="italic">Sick, The Merciful God Remember thee, with the Mercies of Health!</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49307:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Upon <hi rend="blackletterType">Recovery from Sickness.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>10 d. 12 m. 1697, 8.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>It is Written, in Isa. XXXIII. 24.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">The Inhabitant shall not say, I am sick; the people which dwell therein, shall be For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given their Iniquity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">SIckness</hi> having for some Time In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disposed us, it is very seasonable for us, now we are come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again, to consider, <hi rend="italic">What Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement we should make of our late Indisposition?</hi> And the Text now Laid before us, will notably Assist us, to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it suitably!</p>
            <p>The Great God, by his Holy Prophet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49307:4"/>
               <hi rend="italic">Isaiah,</hi> does here foretel, the wonderful Salvation of <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem,</hi> from the Invasion of <hi rend="italic">Sennach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>b.</hi> And here is foretold, a <hi rend="italic">double Blessing,</hi> which the Inhabitants of the Town, should Enjoy, at the Time of that wonderful Salvation.</p>
            <p>First; A <hi rend="italic">Temporal Blessing,</hi> is promised. <hi rend="italic">The Inhabitant shall not say, I am sick.</hi> The Town was to suffer such <hi rend="italic">Hardships,</hi> as use to bring <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> with them. Yea, but saies the Lord, <q rend="margSglQuotes">I will so <hi rend="italic">Preserve</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Restore</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Health</hi> of the Town, that they shall not complain of <hi rend="italic">Sickness:</hi> And, particularly, they shall not by <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> be disabled, from Seizing and Sharing the <hi rend="italic">Prey</hi> of the Defeated Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Next; A <hi rend="italic">Spiritual Blessing</hi> is also pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised: <hi rend="italic">The people which dwell therein, shall be Forgiven their Iniquity.</hi> There was a Blessed <hi rend="italic">Esaias</hi> among them, to plead the <hi rend="italic">Great Sacrifice for the Congregation.</hi> Hence, tho' there were much <hi rend="italic">Iniquity</hi> in the Town, yet God so <hi rend="italic">Forgave</hi> it, for the sake of the pleaded <hi rend="italic">Sacrifice</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Messiah,</hi> that He would not inflict on them the Deadly Desolations which their <hi rend="italic">Iniquity</hi> deserved.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49307:4"/>
            <p>King <hi rend="italic">Hezekiah</hi> seems to have seen, a very peculiar <hi rend="italic">Fulfilment</hi> of this <hi rend="italic">Prophecy.</hi> The Memorable <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Hezekiah,</hi> was as 'tis thought, in that very Juncture of Time, when the City was Besieged by the <hi rend="italic">Assyrians.</hi> But God, in mercy to <hi rend="italic">all the people who dwelt therein,</hi> did, in a few dayes Heal the <hi rend="italic">Malignant Squinancy</hi> of this Eminent <hi rend="italic">Inhabitant.</hi> Yea, (as there had now passed <hi rend="italic">Fifteen</hi> Jubilees of years from the Conquest of <hi rend="italic">Canaan,</hi> and there were to be just <hi rend="italic">Fifteen</hi> Weeks of years from hence to the Captivity in <hi rend="italic">Babylon,</hi> and as <hi rend="italic">Hezekiah</hi> himself, was the <hi rend="italic">Fifteenth</hi> King from the Beginning of the <hi rend="italic">Israelitish</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy!) <hi rend="italic">Fifteen Years</hi> were added unto the Dayes of this Great man, after the <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> which had now been upon him.</p>
            <p>We have Two Things that now ly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our <hi rend="italic">Observation;</hi> and shall in a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct, tho' Feeble, manner, discourse, with all Brevity upon them.</p>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="italic">The First Observation.</hi> The <hi rend="blackletterType">Forgiveness of Sin</hi> is a Blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49307:5"/> that may be <hi rend="blackletterType">Attained,</hi> and should be <hi rend="blackletterType">Desired,</hi> by the Sinful Children of Men.</head>
               <p>What the <hi rend="italic">Angel</hi> said unto the <hi rend="italic">Shepherds</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Bethlehem,</hi> is now proper to be spoken unto the <hi rend="italic">Sinners,</hi> [And, <hi rend="italic">Ah Lord, Such, even Such we are, every one of us!</hi>] which are here met before the Lord: <hi rend="italic">Behold, I bring you Good Tidings of Great Joy!</hi> Those <hi rend="italic">Good Tidings</hi> we have thus Expressed unto us, in Psal. 130.4. <hi rend="italic">There is Forgiveness with thee, that thou mayst be Feared,</hi> O Lord.</p>
               <p>The <hi rend="italic">Oracles</hi> of God assert this Truth a Thousand times over unto us; And, He has Appointed <hi rend="italic">Sacraments</hi> to assure us of it. Yea, This most comfortable Truth is Evident from the <hi rend="blackletterType">Religion,</hi> wherein' God has commanded <hi rend="italic">Sinners</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Draw Near</hi> unto Him. 'Twould be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, for <hi rend="italic">Sinners</hi> to be Directed and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited as they are, unto the <hi rend="italic">wayes</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with God, if they could not be <hi rend="blackletterType">Forgiven</hi> their past Rebellion against Him; or, if His <hi rend="italic">Name</hi> were not, as He hath Himself proclaimed it, <hi rend="italic">The Lord For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49307:5"/> Iniquity, and Transgression, and Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let this vast matter of <hi rend="italic">Meditation</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Consolation,</hi> be with all possible concise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, now summarily set before us, in <hi rend="italic">Three Conclusions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi rend="italic">I.</hi> In the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of Sin,</hi> the Sinner is not only <hi rend="italic">Absolved,</hi> from his cursed <hi rend="italic">Guiltiness,</hi> but also possessed of a perfect <hi rend="italic">Righteousness,</hi> thro' the <hi rend="italic">Imputation</hi> of that <hi rend="italic">Obedience,</hi> which our Lord JESUS CHRIST, as our <hi rend="italic">Surety,</hi> hath yielded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, for his <hi rend="italic">Chosen</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let, first, a few <hi rend="italic">preparatory Assertions,</hi> make our Thoughts ready to take in a Right Notion of this Illustrious Benefit, <hi rend="italic">The Forgiveness of our Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to be Asserted, That we are <hi rend="italic">all Sinners</hi> against the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God, &amp; have brought horrible Ruines on our selves by our <hi rend="italic">Sins.</hi> We have this Assertion, in <hi rend="italic">Ro.</hi> 3.23. <hi rend="italic">All have sinned, and come short of the Glory of God.</hi> We have by our <hi rend="italic">Sins,</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited all the <hi rend="italic">Blessings,</hi> which the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God promised unto the Keepers of that <hi rend="italic">Law;</hi> yea, we have by our <hi rend="italic">Sins</hi> Incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all those <hi rend="italic">Wants</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Woes,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Plagues,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49307:6"/> which the Law has denounced unto them that keep it not.</p>
               <p>Again; It is to be Asserted, That the <hi rend="italic">Chosen</hi> of God, cannot be <hi rend="italic">Rescued,</hi> as He has <hi rend="italic">purposed,</hi> out of their Horrible Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines, except the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God be Answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. We have this Assertion, in Heb. 1.13. <hi rend="italic">Thou canst not Look upon Iniquity.</hi> God by His most wise <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> hath secured the Interests of His Glory; and He is a <hi rend="italic">Judge,</hi> that will by no means have the <hi rend="italic">Equity,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Verity,</hi> of His <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> Impeached.</p>
               <p>Furthermore; It is to be Asserted, That our Lord <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ,</hi> hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to <hi rend="italic">Answer</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God, as a <hi rend="italic">Surety,</hi> on the Behalf of His <hi rend="italic">Chosen.</hi> We have this Assertion, in Heb. 7.22. <hi rend="italic">Jesus was made a Surety.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Son</hi> of God, assuming our <hi rend="italic">Nature,</hi> became a <hi rend="italic">Mediator;</hi> and by becoming a <hi rend="italic">man,</hi> He became ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being Responsible to the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God, for us; for which cause, He actually put Himself, into the Capacity of our <hi rend="italic">Surety,</hi> that by answering the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of the <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> in our <hi rend="italic">Stead,</hi> He might Accomplish the <hi rend="italic">Atonement</hi> with God, for which He was, as our <hi rend="italic">High
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49307:6"/> Priest</hi> concerned: So that He said, unto His <hi rend="italic">Father</hi> concerning <hi rend="italic">Us,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Paul,</hi> (no doubt with some sense of <hi rend="italic">That!</hi>) said unto <hi rend="italic">Philemon,</hi> about his Run away Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi rend="italic">If he has wrong'd thee, or owes thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, put that on my Account!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover; It is to be Asserted, That it was with a <hi rend="italic">mutual Agreement,</hi> between <hi rend="italic">God the Father,</hi> and our <hi rend="italic">Lord Messiah,</hi> that our Lord Jesus Christ became a <hi rend="italic">Surety,</hi> to answer the <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> for His Chosen. We have this Assertion, in Psal. 89.3, 30, 32. <hi rend="italic">I have made a Covenant with my Chosen,— If His Children forsake my Law,—Then will I visit their Transgression with the Rod.</hi> God has indeed bound himself by His <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> That He will be Acknowledged, either in the <hi rend="italic">Obedience,</hi> or in the <hi rend="italic">Destruction,</hi> of His Creatures. But God has not, by His <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> so bound Himself, that He may not Admit of a <hi rend="italic">Surety,</hi> whose <hi rend="italic">Obedience</hi> may go for <hi rend="italic">ours.</hi> Tho' the Old <hi rend="italic">Covenant of Works</hi> do not mention a <hi rend="italic">Surety,</hi> yet a <hi rend="italic">Surety</hi> was mentioned, and engaged and ordered, in the Ancient <hi rend="italic">Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> whereto <hi rend="italic">That</hi> was but Subservi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and wherein <hi rend="italic">God</hi> is become, <hi rend="italic">The God of our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49307:7"/>
               <p>Finally; It is to be Asserted, That our Lord Jesus Christ, ha's according to <hi rend="italic">Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> answered the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God, as our <hi rend="italic">Surety;</hi> both by Enduring the <hi rend="italic">Penalty</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> whereto we had by our <hi rend="italic">Sins</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed our selves, and by Fulfilling the <hi rend="italic">Precept</hi> of it, in doing the whole will of God. We have this Assertion, in 1 Joh. 5.6. <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ came, not by Water only, but by Water and Blood.</hi> He came, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a <hi rend="italic">Purity,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sanctity,</hi> conformed, unto the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God, in all things, but also with <hi rend="italic">Expiatory Sufferings,</hi> to make A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for our Breaches of the <hi rend="italic">Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being furnished with these <hi rend="italic">Preparatory Assertions,</hi> Let us now see, what is done for us in the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of our Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First; In the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of our Sins,</hi> the God of Heaven, does Release us, from the <hi rend="italic">Guiltiness,</hi> wherein we are bound over, to undergo His Infinite Wrath. The <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God, by a <hi rend="italic">Just Sentence,</hi> has condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us to Endure Endless and Easeless <hi rend="italic">Miseries:</hi> But without any prejudice to the <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> God Himself now <hi rend="italic">Acquits</hi> us from that Condemnation and Obligation. 'Tis said: in Rom. 8.1. <hi rend="italic">There is now no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49307:7"/> Condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, more than so; Secondly; In the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of our Sins,</hi> the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven does Invest us with a <hi rend="italic">Righteousness,</hi> which is according to <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> the very <hi rend="italic">Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> of Happiness; Even a <hi rend="italic">Righteousness,</hi> which the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> has annexed <hi rend="italic">Life Eternal</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">Reward</hi> unto: a <hi rend="italic">Righteousness,</hi> which in all things does come up to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the <hi rend="italic">Law.</hi> 'Tis therefore said, in 2 Cor. 5.21. <hi rend="italic">We are made the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, How comes this to pass? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; In the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of our Sins,</hi> the God of Heaven, graciously <hi rend="italic">Imputes</hi> unto us, the <hi rend="italic">Obedience</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ. There was an <hi rend="italic">Habitual Rectitude of Nature,</hi> which our Lord Jesus Christ was Born withal; There was a <hi rend="italic">Course of an Holy Life,</hi> which our Lord Jesus Christ Led for many years together; There was, Lastly, the Exquisite <hi rend="italic">Pain,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Shame,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Horror,</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Curse</hi> due for Sin, Suffered by our Lord Jesus Christ. Now, God <hi rend="italic">Imputes</hi> to us, all this <hi rend="italic">Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, in the <hi rend="italic">For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness of our Sins:</hi> That is to say; He
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49307:8"/> looks on it, as belonging unto <hi rend="italic">Us,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our being Judicially dealt withal, according to the <hi rend="italic">Merit</hi> of it. Hence, tho' it be our <hi rend="italic">Duty</hi> still our selves to <hi rend="italic">Obey</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> of God, and all our coming short thereof, is a <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> for which we are to loath and judge our selves, as worthy of <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> for ever, yet we now <hi rend="italic">Stand as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fault before the Throne of God!</hi> This 'tis to be <hi rend="italic">Forgiven our Iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi rend="italic">II.</hi> By <hi rend="italic">Faith</hi> in our Lord Jesus Christ, and not <hi rend="italic">Without Faith,</hi> and not <hi rend="italic">Before Faith,</hi> is that <hi rend="italic">Blessedness,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of Sin,</hi> to be Attained. In our <hi rend="italic">Bible,</hi> which we may call, <hi rend="italic">The Justification-Office,</hi> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e every where told, as we are in Rom. 5.1. <hi rend="italic">We are Justified by Faith.</hi> But, <hi rend="italic">Faith!</hi> What is <hi rend="italic">That?</hi> It is to <hi rend="italic">Receive</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of Sin,</hi> as the <hi rend="italic">Gift of God,</hi> by our Lord <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rely</hi> upon the Lord <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ</hi> for this <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness.</hi> It is heartily to say, with him, in Phil. 3.9. <hi rend="italic">I suffer the loss of all things, that I may win Christ, and be found in Him, not having my own Righteousness, which is of the Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut that whith is thro' the Faith of Christ,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49307:8"/> the Righteousness which is of God by Faith▪</hi> Indeed, <hi rend="italic">Faith</hi> does not <hi rend="italic">Justify</hi> us, as it is a <hi rend="italic">Work:</hi> 'Tis but <hi rend="italic">Relatively,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally,</hi> that it <hi rend="italic">Justifies</hi> us. <hi rend="italic">Faith,</hi> and only <hi rend="italic">Faith,</hi> has the Honour, to <hi rend="italic">Justify</hi> us, because it carries us unto our Lord Jesus Christ for our <hi rend="italic">Justification,</hi> and ascribes unto the Lord Jesus Christ the Honour of it all. 'Tis true, we read, That <hi rend="italic">Faith is Reckoned unto the Faithful for Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> One thing in it, may be; That tho' <hi rend="italic">Faith</hi> be from the <hi rend="italic">Operation of God</hi> upon us, yet God <hi rend="italic">reckons</hi> it <hi rend="italic">unto us, reckons</hi> it <hi rend="italic">as our own,</hi> accepts it as <hi rend="italic">our Act;</hi> else it could not bring the <hi rend="italic">Righteousness</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, or any thing else, to be <hi rend="italic">ours.</hi> But when 'tis said, <hi rend="italic">Faith is Reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned for Righteousness,</hi> 'tis the Object of our <hi rend="italic">Faith,</hi> which is thereby intended; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi rend="italic">Obedience</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, on which our <hi rend="italic">Faith</hi> is placed. The Soveraign God, has fixed things in this <hi rend="italic">Method;</hi> That upon our being Enabled by Him, to <hi rend="italic">Believe</hi> on our Lord Jesus Christ, our Lord <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ Himself</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi rend="italic">ours,</hi> and so, His <hi rend="italic">Obedience</hi> to God, becomes pleadable by us, as our <hi rend="italic">Title,</hi> to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49307:9"/> all the priviledges of the <hi rend="italic">Righteous</hi> for ever.</p>
               <p>Don't Imagine, to have the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of Sin</hi> granted, <hi rend="italic">Without,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Before, Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> on the Lord Jesus Christ for it. In the <hi rend="italic">Golden Chain of Salvation,</hi> the Links have this Connexion: Rom. 8.30. <hi rend="italic">Whom He called, them He Justifyed.</hi> Now, <hi rend="italic">Faith</hi> is given to us, in our <hi rend="italic">Effectual Calling.</hi> That we are <hi rend="italic">Actually Justified from Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> This is but a vain Imagination! As well say, <hi rend="italic">Sanctified from Eternity,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Glorified from Eternity.</hi> Do! go on, and say, That the people of God never were in any <hi rend="italic">State of Sin</hi> at all! But the <hi rend="italic">Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Truth,</hi> will every where confute you, if you say so. What is the State of every man, while yet an <hi rend="italic">Unbeliever?</hi> Truly, [Joh. 3, 18, 36.] <hi rend="italic">He is condemned, and the Wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> A Rueful State! But how contrary is this, to a State of <hi rend="italic">Justification,</hi> I beseech you? Does not the Scripture say of <hi rend="italic">Believers,</hi> That once they were [Eph. 2, 3.] <hi rend="italic">Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath?</hi> Now, I pray, when was This? It was Before they were <hi rend="italic">Believers.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would ask, Whether every <hi rend="italic">Justified man</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49307:9"/> does not <hi rend="italic">please God?</hi> Yea; But I am sure, [Heb. 11.6.] <hi rend="italic">Without Faith, it is not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to please God.</hi> Then, <hi rend="italic">Without Faith it is not possible to be a Justified man!</hi> What shall I say? If, <hi rend="italic">Justified By Faith,</hi> certainly we are not <hi rend="italic">Justified,</hi> BEFORE <hi rend="italic">it,</hi> or WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUT <hi rend="italic">it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was a Time, when this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, was much Infested with <hi rend="italic">Antinomian</hi> Errors; but a <hi rend="italic">Synod</hi> of our Churches then Damned those Errors, with Deciding; <q rend="margSglQuotes">That we are not <hi rend="italic">Married</hi> and <hi rend="italic">United</hi> unto the Lord Jesus Christ, without <hi rend="italic">Faith</hi> giving an <hi rend="italic">Actual Consent</hi> of Soul unto it; and, That Gods <hi rend="italic">Effectual Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of the Soul unto the Lord Jesus Christ, and the Souls Apprehending by an Act of <hi rend="italic">Faith,</hi> the offered <hi rend="italic">Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, is in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Nature, before Gods Act of <hi rend="italic">Jus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification</hi> upon the Soul.</q> A <hi rend="italic">Decision</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be <hi rend="italic">Held Fast</hi> among us!</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi rend="italic">III.</hi> That man who does not account, the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of Sin,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Blessedness</hi> to be Desired, has <hi rend="italic">Madness in his heart while he Lives, and is going to the Dead.</hi> Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Besotted is that Soul, that Subscribes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49307:10"/> not unto those Thoughts, in Psal. 32.1, 2. <hi rend="italic">Blessed is he, whose Transgression is For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, whose Sin is covered; Blessed is the man, unto whom the Lord Imputeth not Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> God will one day <hi rend="italic">awaken</hi> thy Soul, O man, out of that Besotment!</p>
               <p>Tis to be Admired, how any man, can well enjoy any thing he ha's, till <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> be <hi rend="italic">Forgiven</hi> unto him. Ah! what woful <hi rend="italic">Narcoticks</hi> are there in the Pillow, of that man, that can go to <hi rend="italic">Sleep</hi> to night unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned! Our Good old Mr. <hi rend="italic">Whiting,</hi> the Venerable Pastor of <hi rend="italic">Lyn,</hi> over heard certain Persons very Merry in a Room of an Inn, by which he had occasion to pass: As he pass'd by, he just look'd in, to let fall that p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ge, with much Gravity, upon them, <hi rend="italic">Sirs, If your Sins be all Pardoned, you may very well, be chearful!</hi> And God Thunder-Struck the Souls of some in the Company, with the pungent Remembrance of that passage, all their Dayes. Truly, Sirs, <hi rend="italic">If your Sins be all Pardoned,</hi> You may then, <hi rend="italic">Eat your Bread with Joy, &amp; Drink your Wine with a chearful Heart; for God Accepteth your Works.</hi> But if <hi rend="italic">not,</hi> O miserable Soul, then the <hi rend="italic">Almighty God is Angry with thee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49307:10"/> Every Day,</hi> and thy Heart may break, (if it were not <hi rend="italic">harder than an Adament,</hi> it would break!) under the Terrors of that Thought, <hi rend="italic">God counts me for His Enemy!</hi> A Great Person in the English Nation, being assured, by the <hi rend="italic">Physicians</hi> that his <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> was unavoidably Near unto him, Cry'd out with Hellish Anguish, <hi rend="italic">Oh! that I might Live, though it were but the life of a Toad; for better that than Hell!</hi> Sinner, if thou Dy <hi rend="italic">Unpardoned,</hi> the life of a <hi rend="italic">Toad</hi> will be a better life than thine, throughout Eternal Ages!</p>
               <p>Let me Expostulate with you.</p>
               <p>Consider, How much of <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi rend="italic">Talents,</hi> how heavy <hi rend="italic">Mountains,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> you have lying on you. You may say, <hi rend="italic">The First Sin of the First man, is become just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mine!</hi> You may say, <hi rend="italic">I have an Heart as full of Sin, as a Toad is full of Poison▪</hi> You may say, <hi rend="italic">Ever since I began to Exercise my Reason, I have most Unreasonably broken, every one of the Holy and Just, and Good Commandments, which my God ha's given me.</hi> We may, every one of us, make that sad Lamentation, in Psal. 40.12. <hi rend="italic">Innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable evils have compassed me about, my Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49307:11"/> are more than the Hairs of my Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Consider, What a <hi rend="italic">Dreadful,</hi> what a <hi rend="italic">Doleful,</hi> Thing it is, to have <hi rend="italic">Sin Unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</hi> The Apostle spoke it, as the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallest Thing that could be spoken, <hi rend="italic">Ye are yet in your Sins!</hi> Our Saviour uttered it, as the smartest of all his Thunders, <hi rend="italic">Ye shall Dy in your Sins!</hi> Never was there a more terrible Commination, than that in Amos: 8.7. <hi rend="italic">The Lord hath Sworn, surely I will never forget any of their Works.</hi> Alas, while you are unpardoned, you are in Hourly Danger, of being Siezed by the <hi rend="italic">Eternal Vengeance</hi> of God, and of being made a Sacrifice in the Flames of His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wrath! Sleepy Soul; Thou Sleepest on the <hi rend="italic">Top of a Mast,</hi> and this in the midst of an Horrible Fiery <hi rend="italic">Ocean</hi> too.</p>
               <p>Be perswaded then, to pursue the <hi rend="italic">For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geveness of Sin,</hi> with all <hi rend="italic">Fervency of Soul.</hi> As <hi rend="italic">yet,</hi> it may be had; yea, for the Blackest, and Vilest Sinner among us all, <hi rend="italic">it may be had!</hi> But it will quickly be <hi rend="italic">Too late:</hi> God only knows, how soon, it may be <hi rend="italic">Too late.</hi> Until it be done, <hi rend="italic">Thy Life hangs in doubt before Thee! Our God will Abundantly Pardon;</hi> but then, O Thou
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49307:11"/> Soul in Peril, <hi rend="italic">Seek the Lord, while He may be found!</hi> It may be, <hi rend="italic">To Day;</hi> but no man alive can say, any Further than, <hi rend="italic">To Day!</hi> Wherefore, <hi rend="italic">To Day, To Day,</hi> Oh! That you would <hi rend="italic">hear the Voice of God!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We will now pass to,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="italic">The Second Observation.</hi> The Consideration of <hi rend="blackletterType">Deliverance</hi> from <hi rend="blackletterType">Sickness,</hi> is particularly to provoke our Diligence in Seeking after such a Blessedness.</head>
               <p>Now, there is a CASE, upon which it will be profitable for us, to bestow a few Reflections.</p>
               <p rend="italic">After what manner are we, to Consider the Forgiveness of Sin, in its Relation to a Deliverance from Sickness?</p>
               <p>And we will thus Reflect upon it.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi rend="italic">I.</hi> Let us look upon <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> as the <hi rend="italic">Cause</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sickness.</hi> There are, it may be, <hi rend="italic">Two Thousand Sicknesses;</hi> and indeed, <hi rend="italic">any one of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49307:12"/> them, able to Crush us!</hi> But what is the <hi rend="italic">Cause</hi> of all? Bear in mind, That <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> was that which First brought <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Sinful World, and which yet conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to <hi rend="italic">Sicken</hi> the World, with a World of Diseases. Our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> is in short, <hi rend="italic">Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellum Dei, Pro Peccatis Mundi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First. Remember, That the <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> of our <hi rend="italic">First Parents,</hi> was the <hi rend="italic">First Parent</hi> of all our <hi rend="italic">Sickness.</hi> All our <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses,</hi> are but the Execution, of that Primitive Threatening in Gen. 2.17. <hi rend="italic">In the Day, that thou sinnest thou shalt surely Dy,</hi> If <hi rend="italic">Crudities,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Malignities,</hi> are the <hi rend="italic">Parents</hi> of our <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses,</hi> 'tis very sure, that <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Grand Parent</hi> of them, and the <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> of our <hi rend="italic">First-Parents</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">First Parent</hi> of them all. We read, in Eccl. 9.18. of, <hi rend="italic">ONE Sin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner destroying much Good.</hi> I find, some Jewish <hi rend="italic">Rabbi's</hi> take our Father <hi rend="italic">Adam,</hi> to be meant by that <hi rend="italic">ONE Sinner.</hi> Our <hi rend="italic">Health</hi> is no small part of the <hi rend="italic">Good,</hi> which ha's been <hi rend="italic">Destroy'd</hi> by him. Had our <hi rend="italic">First Parents</hi> Eaten of the <hi rend="italic">Tree of Life,</hi> doubtless a confirm'd State of <hi rend="italic">Perfect Health,</hi> both in Themselves and their Off spring, had been the <hi rend="italic">Fruit</hi> of it. But ours <hi rend="italic">First Parents</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49307:12"/> criminally apply'd themselves to the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden <hi rend="italic">Tree of Knowledge:</hi> This proved a <hi rend="italic">Tree of Death</hi> both to Themselves and their Off-spring; and <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses</hi> are among the <hi rend="italic">Punishments</hi> of that nefandous Crime. Alas; <hi rend="italic">Our Father Are Sowre Grapes, and our Teeth are set on Edge!</hi> When that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression is used about our Lord Jesus Christ, [Heb. 2.9.] <hi rend="italic">He TASTED Death for us;</hi> I make no doubt, that it is an Elegant Allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, unto the <hi rend="italic">Way,</hi> whereby <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> at first came into the World; This was by <hi rend="italic">Tasting</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Forbidden Fruit.</hi> As <hi rend="italic">Death,</hi> so <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> the Inchoation of <hi rend="italic">Death,</hi> is but the Bitter Tast of that unhappy Action! Yea, The <hi rend="italic">Breath</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Old Serpent,</hi> whereto Mankind in our First Parents hearkened, has <hi rend="italic">poisoned</hi> us all. The <hi rend="italic">poison,</hi> which that <hi rend="italic">Serpent,</hi> who is, <hi rend="italic">The Angel of Death,</hi> has insinuated into us, has disturbed our <hi rend="italic">Health,</hi> as well as depraved our <hi rend="italic">Heart. Sin, Sin,</hi> was that which opened the Flood Gates for a Flood of <hi rend="italic">Wretchedness,</hi> to rush in upon the World; and <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> is one Instance of that <hi rend="italic">Wretchedness. Cursed SIN; I Indict thee, this Day, for Murdering of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49307:13"/>
               <p>Secondly. Remember, That the <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> of every <hi rend="italic">Individual man,</hi> does but <hi rend="italic">Repeat</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Renew</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Cause</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> unto him. We are informed, in Psal. 107.17. <hi rend="italic">Pools, because of their Transgression, and because of their Iniquities, are Afflicted,</hi> with Sickness. Indeed <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> sometimes is <hi rend="italic">Naturally</hi> the cause of <hi rend="italic">Sickness.</hi> A <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit,</hi> will <hi rend="italic">Naturally</hi> cause a <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Body. Inordinate Passions</hi> Burn the <hi rend="italic">Threed</hi> of Life. <hi rend="italic">Intemperate Courses</hi> Drown the <hi rend="italic">Lamp</hi> of Life. The Wise man saies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi rend="italic">Uncleanness, It Consumes the Body Plures Occidit Crapula, quam gladius:</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Cup</hi> kills more than the <hi rend="italic">Canon.</hi> And, <hi rend="italic">multos morbos, Fercula multa faciunt;</hi> many <hi rend="italic">Dishes</hi> will breed many <hi rend="italic">Diseases.</hi> Alas, when will men Believe it! The <hi rend="italic">Board</hi> Slayes more than the <hi rend="italic">Sword.</hi> And one may say, <hi rend="italic">By S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ppers and Surfeits, more have been ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d, than all the Physicians in the world ever cured.</hi> The Apostle says about Worldly <hi rend="italic">Griefs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cares, They work Death.</hi> We may add, <hi rend="italic">Ignavum Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> purt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pus.</hi> But <hi rend="italic">Sin is</hi> oftner a <hi rend="italic">Moral</hi> Cause of <hi rend="italic">Sickness.</hi> What are <hi rend="italic">Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,</hi> but the <hi rend="italic">Rods,</hi> wherewith God cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49307:13"/> His own offending Children? Pious <hi rend="italic">Asa,</hi> takes a wrong step, and he is <hi rend="italic">Diseas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Feet</hi> for it; God sends the <hi rend="italic">Gout,</hi> upon him. And what are they, but the <hi rend="italic">Vindictive Strokes</hi> of Wrath, wherewith God Revenges Himself upon the Children of Wrath? <hi rend="italic">Jehoram</hi> did a <hi rend="italic">Bloody Thing;</hi> and, Lo, <hi rend="italic">his Bowels fell out by reason of his Sickness;</hi> God smites him with a <hi rend="italic">Bloody Flux</hi> for it. Hence, our <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses,</hi> are in the New Testament, called by a Name, that hath, <hi rend="italic">Scourges,</hi> in the Signification of it. [Ponder, at <hi rend="italic">Liesure,</hi> Exod 15.26. and Deut. 28.21, 22, 27; 35, 60, 61. And say not, as he to whom the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness,</hi> was presented, <hi rend="italic">I am not at Liesure!</hi>] Ah! <hi rend="italic">Sin;</hi> How mischievous art thou? A man may say of every <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> when he meets with it, <hi rend="italic">Have I found thee, O mine Enemy!</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Soul</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Body</hi> constitute <hi rend="italic">one person;</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Body</hi> is unto the <hi rend="italic">Soul,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Instrument</hi> of Iniquity: hence for the <hi rend="italic">Sins</hi> of the one, there come <hi rend="italic">Sufferings</hi> on the other. <hi rend="italic">Syrs,</hi> Be afraid of <hi rend="italic">Sin:</hi> I tell you, 'Tis a very <hi rend="italic">Unwholsome Thing.</hi> When you are going to drink the <hi rend="italic">Stolen Waters</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sin: There's Death in the Pot.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49307:14"/>
               <p>Thirdly. Hence under <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> we should make a solemn Enquiry after <hi rend="italic">Sin.</hi> As upon other <hi rend="italic">Disasters,</hi> there was that call given, in Hag. 1.5, 7. <hi rend="italic">Consider your wayes:</hi> 'tis to be heard most sensibly in our <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses.</hi> There is a <hi rend="italic">Self Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> incumbent upon <hi rend="italic">All</hi> men; upon <hi rend="italic">Sick</hi> men, 'tis peculiarly incumbent. Pray, Let our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> be it self such an <hi rend="italic">Emetie</hi> as to make us <hi rend="italic">Vomit</hi> up our <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> with a penitent <hi rend="italic">Confession</hi> of it. A Time there was, when <hi rend="italic">Sacramental Profanations,</hi> were Chastized with <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses</hi> among the <hi rend="italic">Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians;</hi> They had not come in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly manner to the <hi rend="italic">Body</hi> of the Lord, and God Rebuked it, with <hi rend="italic">Disorders</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Theirs. (Compare 2 Chron. 30.20.) Now, says the Apostle, <hi rend="italic">Judge your selves.</hi> Indeed, <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> does not always come, to manage a <hi rend="italic">Controversy</hi> of God with us, for some <hi rend="italic">Iniquity.</hi> A <hi rend="italic">Job,</hi> that <hi rend="italic">Perfect and Upright man,</hi> may have his <hi rend="italic">Ulcera Syriaca,</hi> [so tragically described by <hi rend="italic">Aretaeus,</hi> and admirably answering the <hi rend="italic">Diagnosticks,</hi> which the Sacred Writ has given us of <hi rend="italic">Jobs</hi> Distemper:] to <hi rend="italic">Try</hi> his Patience. 'Tis said, of that <hi rend="italic">Man of God, Elisha,</hi> He
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49307:14"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">fell Sick, of his Sickness, whereof he died:</hi> It seems he had been <hi rend="italic">Sick</hi> sometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Our Lord may have a <hi rend="italic">Lazarus,</hi> of whom it shall be said, <hi rend="italic">One whom thou Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest is Sick.</hi> Strange! <hi rend="italic">Diseases</hi> may be <hi rend="italic">Love Tokens.</hi> A <hi rend="italic">Timothy,</hi> that Rare Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, whom one of the Ancients calls, <hi rend="italic">An Admirable Young man,</hi> may be, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with <hi rend="italic">Often Infirmities.</hi> Our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ is to be <hi rend="italic">visited,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> of His Dearest <hi rend="italic">Brethren: (Lord, That ever thou shouldest call them so!)</hi> But yet it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes us, to be very Inquisitive, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous, lest there be <hi rend="italic">Wrath in our Sickness,</hi> and Thoughtful, <hi rend="italic">What is the Controversy?</hi> Yea, Be the <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> never so Light.</p>
               <p>Our Excellent <hi rend="italic">Mitchel,</hi> being but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoded with an <hi rend="italic">Hoarse Cold,</hi> wrote thus upon it, in his Diary. <q rend="margSglQuotes">My <hi rend="italic">Sin is</hi> Legible in the <hi rend="italic">Chastisement. Cold</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi rend="italic">Cold</hi> Prayers, (my <hi rend="italic">voice</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Prayer, i. e.</hi> my Spirit of Prayer fearfully gone,) my <hi rend="italic">Coldness</hi> in my whole <hi rend="italic">Conversation,</hi> Chastized with a <hi rend="italic">Cold:</hi> I fear that I have not Improved my <hi rend="italic">voice</hi> for God formerly, as I might have done, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore He now takes it from me.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49307:15"/>
               <p>I have somewhere met with the Papers of another, who under the pains of the <hi rend="italic">Tooth-ach,</hi> thus expressed himself. <q rend="margSglQuotes">In the <hi rend="italic">pains,</hi> that were now upon me, I set my self, as well as I could, for my <hi rend="italic">pains,</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Search and Try my ways.</hi> Espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, Whether I had not <hi rend="italic">Sinned</hi> with my <hi rend="italic">Teeth.</hi> Particularly, in Two Things; By Sinful, Graceless, Excessive <hi rend="italic">Eating;</hi> And by <hi rend="italic">Evil Speeches,</hi> for there are, <hi rend="italic">Literae Dentales</hi> used in them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Sirs, How Copious a <hi rend="italic">Theme,</hi> is here to be Insisted on! But I must Insist no further.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi rend="italic">II.</hi> Both Under <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> and After it, we should be more concerned for being Saved from <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> than from <hi rend="italic">Sickness.</hi> Our <hi rend="italic">Sins,</hi> what are they, but the Terrible <hi rend="italic">Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,</hi> under which our <hi rend="italic">Souls,</hi> are fearfully Languishing and Perishing. A <hi rend="italic">Sinful Soul,</hi> is a <hi rend="italic">Sickly Soul. Original Sin,</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Plague of the Heart.</hi> Every <hi rend="italic">Lust,</hi> is a <hi rend="italic">Distemper</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Soul.</hi> An <hi rend="italic">Unsteady</hi> Soul, ha's a <hi rend="italic">Palsey.</hi> A <hi rend="italic">Wanton</hi> Soul, ha's a <hi rend="italic">Feaver.</hi> A <hi rend="italic">Worldly</hi> Soul ha's a <hi rend="italic">Dropsy.</hi> An <hi rend="italic">Angry</hi> Soul, ha's an <hi rend="italic">Erisypelas. Envy,</hi> is a <hi rend="italic">Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49307:15"/> in the Soul. Whenever we have Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we have cause to say, <hi rend="italic">Lord, HEAL my Soul, for I have Sinned!</hi> Now, <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> is to Awaken our concern, first for the <hi rend="italic">Pardon</hi> of such Maladies in our Souls, and so for a <hi rend="italic">Power</hi> against them all.</p>
               <p>First; <hi rend="italic">Under Sickness,</hi> what should be our chief concern? It should be <hi rend="italic">That,</hi> in Psal 25.18. <hi rend="italic">Lord, Look upon my Affliction and my Pain, and Forgive all my Sin.</hi> If it be then put unto us, <hi rend="italic">What lies heaviest now upon you?</hi> Say not, <hi rend="italic">My Sickness:</hi> but say, <hi rend="italic">My Sinfulness! That I have done so little Service for my Lord Jesus Christ: That I have mispent so much of my Precious Time: That I have made no more Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for Eternity: And, That I am still so Selfish, and Slothful, and Sensual, and Carnal, and Alienated from the Life of God!</hi> And for to Quicken this our concern under our <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> we are to think, <hi rend="italic">What will become of us, if we Dy Unpardoned; what will become of us, throughout Eternal Ages?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next; <hi rend="italic">After Sickness,</hi> What should be our chief concern? It should be <hi rend="italic">That,</hi> in Psal. 103.3. <hi rend="italic">Bless the Lord, O my Soul, who Forgiveth all thine Iniquities, who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49307:16"/> Healeth all thy Diseases.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Iniquities</hi> are to be taken away <hi rend="italic">First,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Then</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Diseases.</hi> Let us not count our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> well gone, Except our <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> be gone too. But let us now put this unto our selves, <hi rend="italic">Am I now more Assured of my being Pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than I was before? Am I in better Terms with Heaven? Can I see and say, Tis in Love to my Soul, that God ha's brought me back from the Pit of Corruption?</hi> It should now be more of our care, That our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> be Removed in <hi rend="italic">Mercy,</hi> than ever it was, That it should be <hi rend="italic">Removed at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, In Fine; To this End, the <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> which <hi rend="italic">Enfeebles</hi> us, must make us Fly more <hi rend="italic">Vigorously</hi> than ever, to the <hi rend="italic">Expiatory Sacrifice</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, for the <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness of our Sin.</hi> My Brethren, Our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> is utterly lost upon us, if it render not a CHRIST more <hi rend="italic">Precious</hi> unto us than ever He was, and instruct us not how to make more <hi rend="italic">Use</hi> of Him. As the <hi rend="italic">Sick,</hi> in the Gospels, much cryed out for, <hi rend="italic">A Christ!</hi> So <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> is to Teach us, the <hi rend="italic">Worth</hi> of a <hi rend="italic">Christ,</hi> and cause us more to see, that without a <hi rend="italic">Christ,</hi> we are undone
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49307:16"/> for ever. There is a <hi rend="italic">Ransome,</hi> which a <hi rend="italic">Sick man</hi> is to be minded of; that <hi rend="italic">Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some,</hi> in Job 33.34.—<hi rend="italic">He is chastened with pain upon his Bed, his Flesh is consumed away, his soul draweth nigh to the Grave, Then God is gracious to him, and saith, Deliver him from going down to the Pit, I have found a Ransome.</hi> Sirs, When we are <hi rend="italic">Sick,</hi> let us Behold our Lord Jesus Christ, as <hi rend="italic">Going down into the Pit</hi> for us, and plead that <hi rend="italic">Ransome</hi> that we may not our selves <hi rend="italic">Go down.</hi> In the <hi rend="italic">Directories</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Visiting the Sick,</hi> used many Ages ago, the <hi rend="italic">Sick</hi> were directed to say, <hi rend="italic">Lord, I place the Death of my Saviour Jesus Christ, between Thee and my Sins.</hi> Tis Impossible to say a Better Thing than <hi rend="italic">That!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> our Addresses must be made unto our Lord Jesus Christ, of whom 'tis said, in Math. 8.17. <hi rend="italic">Himself Bare our Sicknesses.</hi> Indeed, we cannot say, That there were any proper <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses,</hi> among the <hi rend="italic">Sufferings</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ; We do not find, that He was ever properly <hi rend="italic">Sick.</hi> His <hi rend="italic">Body</hi> being form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by a Special Efficacy of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Spirit,</hi> seems to have been of so Exact a <hi rend="italic">Temper,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49307:17"/> as to be less liable unto <hi rend="italic">Diseases</hi> than other men. But our Lord Jesus Christ <hi rend="italic">Bare our Sicknesses,</hi> because, as 'tis else-where said for it, <hi rend="italic">He bare our Sins;</hi> which are the <hi rend="italic">Cause</hi> of our <hi rend="italic">Sicknesses.</hi> Wherefore, In every <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> let us repair to the <hi rend="italic">Death</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, and Struggle with our <hi rend="italic">Unbelief,</hi> more than with our <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> until we are able to say; <hi rend="italic">Lord, my whole Dependence is on my Lord Jesus Christ, who ha's made Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the Sins, for which thou hast made me Sick in smiting me!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I'le Recite you, a Contempla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of the Blessed <hi rend="italic">Austin's,</hi> which under <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> may be the sweetest <hi rend="italic">Anodyne</hi> of our uneasy minds. <q rend="margSglQuotes">There lay Extended over the whole World, a Great Instance of <hi rend="italic">Sickness;</hi> That is to say, All <hi rend="italic">Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> Subject unto many <hi rend="italic">Diseases</hi> both of <hi rend="italic">Soul</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Body:</hi> And therefore there is come into the World, that Great <hi rend="italic">Physician,</hi> by whose <hi rend="italic">Wounds we are Healed.</hi> Indeed, we see, that the <hi rend="italic">Soul</hi> of man, labours under the Numberless <hi rend="italic">Diseases,</hi> which are its <hi rend="italic">Vices.</hi> And the <hi rend="italic">Body</hi> of man Suffers more <hi rend="italic">Diseases,</hi> than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49307:17"/> Creature. But, O Admirable and Amiable matter, and a thing full of Compassionate Goodness! <hi rend="italic">[Fusus est Sanguis medici, et factum est Medicamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Phrenetici!]</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Blood</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sician</hi> being shed, becomes the <hi rend="italic">Cure</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Patient!</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi rend="italic">III.</hi> Being <hi rend="italic">Delivered from Sickness,</hi> Let us not be content without the <hi rend="italic">Marks</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sin Forgiven</hi> upon us. When we no more say, <hi rend="italic">I am Sick,</hi> Let us make sure of those <hi rend="italic">Marks,</hi> which will help us with Good As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance to say, <hi rend="italic">I am Forgiven my Iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the <hi rend="italic">Marks,</hi> by which we may discern, that we come out of <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> with our <hi rend="italic">Iniquity Forgiven</hi> unto us, will be found in our Answering the <hi rend="italic">Ends,</hi> for which our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> came upon us: And our coming out of <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Gold out of the Fire.</hi> Wherefore, let us thus <hi rend="italic">Question</hi> our selves.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Quest. I.</label> After our <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> do we sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely set our selves, to <hi rend="italic">Reform</hi> all our <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> more than ever in our Lives before? It was <hi rend="italic">wholesome</hi> Advice unto a <hi rend="italic">Sick man,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49307:18"/> in Job 34 31. <hi rend="italic">Surely, It is meet to be said unto God, I have born Chastisement, I wil<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> not offend any more.</hi> Truly, one main <hi rend="italic">Er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rand</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> is to <hi rend="italic">Embitter</hi> our <hi rend="italic">Si<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> unto us; the <hi rend="italic">Language</hi> of it, is, <hi rend="italic">Thy way, and thy Doings have procured these things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, this is thy Sinfulness, because it is Bitter.</hi> As the famous <hi rend="italic">Olevian,</hi> upon a <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> could say, <hi rend="italic">Ex hoc morbo didici quid sit peccatum;</hi> By <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> I have Lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned what <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> is! Thus, under our <hi rend="italic">Sick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness,</hi> we have been worse than <hi rend="italic">Deliriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> if we have not argued at this Rate; <q rend="margSglQuotes">My <hi rend="italic">Sin brought this my Sickness upon me;</hi> may thank my <hi rend="italic">Sin</hi> for <hi rend="italic">This;</hi> Now<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi rend="italic">Effect</hi> be so <hi rend="italic">Bitter,</hi> what is the <hi rend="italic">Cause</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> My <hi rend="italic">Sins</hi> are worse than all the <hi rend="italic">pains</hi> o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> my <hi rend="italic">Head,</hi> my <hi rend="italic">Side,</hi> my <hi rend="italic">Feet;</hi> for my <hi rend="italic">Sins</hi> brought these my <hi rend="italic">pains</hi> upon me▪</q> Well then; Are we grown more <hi rend="italic">Sick</hi> o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> by being Laid on a <hi rend="italic">Bed of Sickness▪</hi> Do we see our <hi rend="italic">Commissions</hi> of what i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi rend="italic">Forbidden,</hi> in the Commands of God, and <hi rend="italic">Reform</hi> them? Do we see our <hi rend="italic">Omissio<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of what is <hi rend="italic">Required,</hi> in the Commands o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> God, and <hi rend="italic">Reform</hi> them? If it be not so Then take, O man, that Awful Warning
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49307:18"/> of Heaven, <hi rend="italic">Thou art made whole, Sin no more, Lest a worse Thing do come unto thee.</hi> But if our <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> have by an Holy <hi rend="italic">Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoresis,</hi> carried off our <hi rend="italic">Sin,</hi> Then we that no longer say, <hi rend="italic">I am Sick,</hi> are, <hi rend="italic">Forgiven our Iniquity!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Quest. II.</label> After our <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> do we more zealously than ever, set our selves to <hi rend="italic">Glorify</hi> our Lord Jesus Christ? One that had been <hi rend="italic">Brought Low,</hi> but been <hi rend="italic">help'd,</hi> thought it Reasonable then to say, in Psal. 116.12. <hi rend="italic">What shall I Render to the Lord, for all His Benefits towards me?</hi> Let us not come out of <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> without such an Ingenuous, <hi rend="italic">Quid Retribuam?</hi> We owe our <hi rend="italic">Lives</hi> unto our Lord Jesus Christ; Are we now more studious, <hi rend="italic">How to Live unto Him?</hi> Being Rescued from <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> do we study to be more <hi rend="italic">Fruitful</hi> in our whole <hi rend="italic">Conversation,</hi> That our Lord Jesus Christ may be more Acknowledged, by every part of our <hi rend="italic">Good Conversation in Him?</hi> And, Do we Study to be more <hi rend="italic">Useful</hi> in every <hi rend="italic">Capa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity,</hi> That in every <hi rend="italic">Relation,</hi> which we sustain, we may do <hi rend="italic">more Good</hi> than ever we did? Yea, Do we Study now, to do some <hi rend="italic">Special Thing</hi> for the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49307:19"/> Name of our Lord Jesus Christ? Of old, They that were Cured of any <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> were bound for to pay a price, which they called, a ΣΩΣΤΡΟΝ, unto their <hi rend="italic">Healer.</hi> It is our Lord Jesus Christ, that hath been, <hi rend="italic">The Lord our Healer.</hi> Do we gratefully think, <hi rend="italic">What special Thing shall I now do, for the Honour of my Healer?</hi> Then, we that no longer say, <hi rend="italic">I am Sick,</hi> are, <hi rend="italic">For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given our Iniquity!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Quest. III.</label> After our <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> are we more <hi rend="italic">Sick</hi> of this <hi rend="italic">vain World,</hi> than ever we were, since we came into the <hi rend="italic">World?</hi> Of the <hi rend="italic">Sick,</hi> 'tis said, in Psal. 107.18. <hi rend="italic">Their Soul abhors all manner of meat,</hi> when they <hi rend="italic">draw near unto the Gates of Death.</hi> Has our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> made us to <hi rend="italic">Abhor,</hi> or to <hi rend="italic">Despise,</hi> those Gratifications of our <hi rend="italic">Flesh,</hi> which once were as the <hi rend="italic">chief Good,</hi> unto us? As <hi rend="italic">Esau</hi> said, when he was <hi rend="italic">Faint, Behold, I am at the point of Death, and what Good will this Birthright do unto me?</hi> Thus, has the <hi rend="italic">Faintness</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> brought us to say, <hi rend="italic">Behold, I shall Dy shortly, and what Good is there in all the Pleasures, and all the Riches, and all the Honours of this Deceitful World?</hi> And are these Dispositions conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49307:19"/> and confirmed in us, after we com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of <hi rend="italic">Sickness?</hi> We are too ready, to account this <hi rend="italic">present Evil World</hi> our Home, and promise our selves Long <hi rend="italic">Rest</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Peace,</hi> and much <hi rend="italic">Satisfaction</hi> in <hi rend="italic">this World.</hi> But, <hi rend="italic">This our way is our Folly!</hi> And a Fault it is, that our God will never En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in those, for whom He hath <hi rend="italic">Reserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Inheritance in Heaven, Uncorrupted and Undefiled, and that fadeth not away.</hi> Now, upon our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> is this <hi rend="italic">present World,</hi> made so <hi rend="italic">Evil</hi> unto us, that we are even <hi rend="italic">Sick</hi> of being here; and has it fill'd us with such Thoughts as these:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margSglQuotes">My Lord Jesus Christ, hath <hi rend="italic">bought</hi> for us, a <hi rend="italic">better World</hi> than <hi rend="italic">This.</hi> Wherefore <hi rend="italic">Awake,</hi> O my Soul, <hi rend="italic">Awake!</hi> Rouse up; <hi rend="italic">Dream</hi> not of Abiding in such an <hi rend="italic">Evil World</hi> as <hi rend="italic">This:</hi> But, <hi rend="italic">Set thy Affections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Things that are above!</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Then, We that no Longer say, <hi rend="italic">I am Sick,</hi> are, <hi rend="italic">Forgiven our Iniquity!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Quest. IV.</label> After we have been <hi rend="italic">made Low,</hi> by <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> are we more <hi rend="italic">Lowly,</hi> and Humble in our <hi rend="italic">Spirit,</hi> than ever hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? <hi rend="italic">Morbi Corporis ad Inhibendam Animi superbiam, sunt Accommodatissimi.</hi> We are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49307:20"/> never fit, for either <hi rend="italic">Comfort</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Service,</hi> but when Lying very <hi rend="italic">Low,</hi> before the Lord. Now, we are <hi rend="italic">brought Low</hi> by <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> that so we may Lay our selves <hi rend="italic">Low.</hi> Is this the Issue of it! When <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> has been Threatning to Lay us in the <hi rend="italic">Dust,</hi> has it caus'd us, to Lay our selves there, and made us with Humility to say, with <hi rend="italic">Job,</hi> after he had been <hi rend="italic">Sick, Now I abhor my self as in Dust and Ashes? Luther</hi> noted it, That when he had any <hi rend="italic">special piece of work</hi> to do for the Church of God, some Fit of <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> usually came to <hi rend="italic">Humble</hi> him, and <hi rend="italic">prepare</hi> him for it. This, This was the occasion of the <hi rend="italic">Thorn in the Flesh,</hi> with which that Great Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord Jesus Christ, the Apostle <hi rend="italic">Paul,</hi> was Exercised. [2 Cor. 12.7.] There has been much Asking, What was the Apostles <hi rend="italic">Thorn in the Flesh?</hi> There have been some Expositions given of it, which carry in them, an unjust Affront unto that Heavenly and Laborious Man of God. Whereas, there is nothing so probable, as a Fit of <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in it. I will not be positive, with <hi rend="italic">Austin,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jerom,</hi> That it was a grievous
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49307:20"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">Head ache;</hi> or, with <hi rend="italic">Tertullian,</hi> That it was a <hi rend="italic">pain</hi> from a Cold, in one side of his <hi rend="italic">Head;</hi> or with <hi rend="italic">Aquinas,</hi> That it was the <hi rend="italic">Iliac Passion:</hi> or with some others, That it was the <hi rend="italic">Ephialtes,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Vertigo,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Gout.</hi> Nevertheless, it seems most probably, to be some sore <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> upon his <hi rend="italic">Body,</hi> that was the Apostles, <hi rend="italic">Thorn in the Flesh.</hi> He pray'd, That he might be set at Liberty from that <hi rend="italic">Sickness;</hi> but God would not wholly set him at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, God would Employ a <hi rend="italic">Sickly man,</hi> in the work of the Gospel, and neither his <hi rend="italic">Labour,</hi> nor <hi rend="italic">Success</hi> therein should be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, by his being so <hi rend="italic">Sickly:</hi> but his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi rend="italic">Sickly,</hi> made him so <hi rend="italic">Humble,</hi> as to <hi rend="italic">Fit</hi> him for his Work exceedingly. Let a man be never so Eminent an Instrument, for the Glory of the Lord Jesus Christ, <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> will cause him to contemn all the Applause of his Admirers, and it will cause him to Ascribe unto the Lord Jesus Christ, the whole Glory of all that shall be done by him. To make this, the more Efficacious, a Minister of a <hi rend="italic">Pauline Soul,</hi> must have, <hi rend="italic">A Messenger of Satan to buffet him,</hi> with his <hi rend="italic">Thorn in the Flesh.</hi> I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49307:21"/> suspect, that the Apostle, in <hi rend="italic">that,</hi> may allude unto the Story of <hi rend="italic">Micajah.</hi> That Minister of God, had a <hi rend="italic">Rapture into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> where he had a Vision of wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Things. After this <hi rend="italic">Abundance of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> he was <hi rend="italic">Buffeted</hi> by a <hi rend="italic">Messenger of Satan;</hi> A <hi rend="italic">Zedekiah,</hi> a man full of <hi rend="italic">Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> then <hi rend="italic">Smote him on the Cheek.</hi> Thus, <hi rend="italic">Quaere,</hi> Whether, the <hi rend="italic">Messenger of Satan,</hi> accompanying the <hi rend="italic">Thorn in the Flesh,</hi> unto this Minister of God, may not be a <hi rend="italic">Wicked</hi> man, whom <hi rend="italic">Satan</hi> had permission to Possess and Inspire, for the Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Faithful Preacher of Christ? I Leave it.</p>
               <p>And I only say; Has our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> made us more Apprehensive, of our <hi rend="italic">Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Baseness?</hi> Being just pluck'd from the mouths of <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> whereto our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> was casting of us down, do we with an Humble Soul, say, <hi rend="italic">Lord, I am a Worm, and no man!</hi> Do we, Like <hi rend="italic">Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ah,</hi> now <hi rend="italic">Walk softly all our years,</hi> in the Remembrance of the <hi rend="italic">Bitterness of our Soul,</hi> which we felt in our <hi rend="italic">Bitter Sickness?</hi> Are we become <hi rend="italic">Nothing,</hi> and is <hi rend="italic">God,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Christ,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Grace,</hi> become <hi rend="italic">All</hi> to us, by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49307:21"/> the <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> which was bringing us to <hi rend="italic">Nothing?</hi> Then, We that no longer say, <hi rend="italic">I am Sick,</hi> are, <hi rend="italic">Forgiven our Iniquity!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, <hi rend="italic">Son, Be of Good Cheer, Thy Sins are Forgiven thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Quest. V.</label> Hath God made us careful to ascribe the whole <hi rend="italic">Honour</hi> of our <hi rend="italic">De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from Sickness,</hi> unto our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ alone? It is the property of a man that ha's had <hi rend="italic">many Sins Forgiven</hi> him, to <hi rend="italic">Love much</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ, through whom it is, that we receive our <hi rend="italic">Forgiveness:</hi> But <hi rend="italic">much Love</hi> to our Lord Jesus Christ, will teach us to set upon His Head alone, the <hi rend="italic">Crown,</hi> as of every other Enjoyment, so of that <hi rend="italic">Cure,</hi> wherein any <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> has been relieved. It is to be hoped, That <hi rend="italic">Before</hi> we had our <hi rend="italic">Cure,</hi> we plac'd our <hi rend="italic">Hope</hi> on our Lord Jesus Christ alone, for our <hi rend="italic">Help.</hi> It was a great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight of King <hi rend="italic">Asa,</hi> when Sick, in 2 Chron. 16.12. <hi rend="italic">In his Disease, he sought not unto the Lord, but unto the Physicians.</hi> It ha's been Conjectured, that some of <hi rend="italic">Asa's</hi> Ancestors had been <hi rend="italic">Medically</hi> disposed, and Students in the <hi rend="italic">Art of Healing.</hi> From hence they might have their <hi rend="italic">Name;</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Asa,</hi> is the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49307:22"/> Chaldee word for a <hi rend="italic">Physician.</hi> Possibly for this Cause, this King had the higher Esteem for those who were skill'd in <hi rend="italic">Medicine,</hi> and put such Confidence in them, as to neglect, <hi rend="italic">The Lord,</hi> the Author and Giver of Health. Be this, how it will; 'tis to be hoped, that, though we have been found in the use of <hi rend="italic">Means</hi> for our Health, and prudently made use of the <hi rend="italic">Physician,</hi> as an <hi rend="italic">Ordinance of God,</hi> yet we have not Relyed upon these <hi rend="italic">Means,</hi> but upon the Lord Jesus Christ alone, who is the <hi rend="italic">Health of our Countenance, and our God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, <hi rend="italic">After</hi> we have our <hi rend="italic">Cure,</hi> Don't we <hi rend="italic">Forget</hi> the Hand that hath <hi rend="italic">Healed our Diseases?</hi> Are we not like the Nine <hi rend="italic">Lepers,</hi> who being brought out of their <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> by the Lord Jesus Christ, went away without ever taking any more Notice of Him? and so, without being <hi rend="italic">Forgiven</hi> their <hi rend="italic">Iniquitie!</hi> Or, don't we come out of our <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> instead of being <hi rend="italic">Forgiven</hi> our <hi rend="italic">Iniquity,</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">Dog</hi> Scrambling out of the <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> which he has been thrown into, Shaking himself a little, and running away, as much a <hi rend="italic">Dog</hi> still as ever?</p>
               <p>Sirs, If we come <hi rend="italic">Forgiven,</hi> out of a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49307:22"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> we shall be mindful of the <hi rend="italic">Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences,</hi> which we have had, of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Benignity towards us in it. It may be, there ha's been some Remarkable <hi rend="italic">Answer of Prayer,</hi> in our Deliverance: It may not be Forgotten. Truly, I cannot without some Delight read one passage, in the <hi rend="italic">Great Austin,</hi> upon the occasion of a Malady, so common, that People Scarce count <hi rend="italic">Prayer</hi> to have any concernment about it. His words, (in his, <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>) are these.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margSglQuotes">Lord, Thou didst Afflict me, with <hi rend="italic">Pain of the Teeth;</hi> and when it was so great, that I could not speak, it came into my mind, to admonish my Friends present to Pray for me, unto the <hi rend="italic">God of all Health.</hi> Writing this on <hi rend="italic">Wax,</hi> I gave it 'em to Read; and as soon as we kneeled down, the pain went away. I was amazed, I confess, my Lord, my God; for I had never found any thing like it, in all my Life.</q>
               </p>
               <p>All that I have now to say, is;</p>
               <p>Ha's God given us, an Heart, for to Acknowledge the <hi rend="italic">Merit</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, as <hi rend="italic">Purchasing</hi> our Deliverance from
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49307:23"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sickness?</hi> It is said, in 1 Pet. 2.24. <hi rend="italic">By His Stripes ye were Healed.</hi> All we have been like <hi rend="italic">Run away Servants,</hi> [and the Apostle is there discoursing to <hi rend="italic">Servants!</hi>] and we deserve <hi rend="italic">Stripes</hi> for our thus Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away from the <hi rend="italic">Service</hi> of God. In <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> there are some of our Deserved <hi rend="italic">Stripes</hi> laid upon us; but when we come out of <hi rend="italic">Sickness,</hi> do we, with a Thankful Soul make this Acknowledgment; <hi rend="italic">My Lord Jesus Christ, ha's felt the Stripes that were due to me, and thus tis, that I am Healed!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ha's God given us an Heart, for to Acknowledge the <hi rend="italic">Power</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ, as <hi rend="italic">Bestowing</hi> our Deliverance from <hi rend="italic">Sickness?</hi> It was said in Mal. 4.2. <hi rend="italic">To you that Fear my Name, shall the Sun of Righteousness arise, with Healing in His Wings.</hi> In the Eastern parts of the World, it ha's been a Custome among the poor Pagans there, That when they have Ineffectually Tryed all ordinary wayes, for the Succour of their <hi rend="italic">Sick Folks,</hi> they would Expose them abroad unto the <hi rend="italic">Sun,</hi> Expecting that the Beams of the <hi rend="italic">Sun,</hi> would perform for them, what could be no other wayes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49307:23"/> Yea, but instead of this, do's our Soul, now make this Thankful Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi rend="italic">Nothing would Save me out of my Sickness, until that Sun of Righteousness, my Lord Jesus Christ, arose upon me, with Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in His Wings!</hi> Truly, These Disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in us will argue, that when we no longer say, <hi rend="italic">I am Sick,</hi> we are also <hi rend="italic">Forgiven our Iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if this be our Case, how happily are we <hi rend="italic">Prepared,</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Next Sickness</hi> that shall <hi rend="italic">Visit</hi> us? Perhaps, it will not be long, before another <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> be upon us; but being <hi rend="italic">Forgiven our Iniquity,</hi> We may Refresh our selves, with such Thoughts, as I find the famous Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cotton,</hi> before ever he stood in the Pulpit of the Church, where I now stand, writing to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanael Rogers,</hi> when that Excellent than, was discouraged by <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> often distress<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him. <q rend="margSglQuotes">Sir, You know who said it, <hi rend="italic">Unmortifyed Stren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th lostet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d to Hell, but S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ctifyed Weakness Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th fast to Heaven</hi> Let not y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur <hi rend="italic">Spirit</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, though your <hi rend="italic">Body</hi> do: Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r <hi rend="italic">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in Gods sight; your <hi rend="italic">Hairs are Numbred;</hi> and the Number and measure
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49307:24"/> of your Fainting Fits, and Wearisome Nights, are weighed, and limited by His Hand, who hath given you the Lord Jesus Christ, to <hi rend="italic">take upon Him your Infirmities, and bear your Sicknesses.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And then, my Brethren, if our <hi rend="italic">Sickness</hi> come upon us, while we have yet <hi rend="italic">Youth</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Strength</hi> enough in our years, to do any more work for our Lord Jesus Christ, we may sweetly Express that Lovely <hi rend="italic">Contradiction</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Christianity; Vitam habere in patientia, mortem in Desiderio:</hi> To say, on the one side, <hi rend="italic">I know that the Hour of my Departure, will be the best Hour that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I saw: when I Depart, I shall be with Christ, which is by far the best of all: I shall be then Lodg'd among the Angels of God; and I Long to be so! I Long for it, with Joy unspeakable and full of Glory!</hi> To say, at the same Time, on the other side, <hi rend="italic">Yet for all this, I ask to Live, that I may Serve Him who is my Life; I am heartily, most heartily willing, to stay among the Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Temptations of this Evil World, that I may Serve the dear Name of my Lord Jesus Christ, in a World, where I have Sinn'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi>
               </p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:49307:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>